<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
	  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc2865 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc5997 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5997.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc7749 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7749.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc4668 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4668.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc4669 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4669.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc4670 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4670.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc4671 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4671.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc3579 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3579.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc4270 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4270.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc1321 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1321.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc5080 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5080.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc5580 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5580.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc3579 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3579.xml'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="std" consensus="true" ipr="trust200902"
     docName="draft-donnelly-radius-loop-detection-00" submissionType="IETF">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Loop Detection for RADIUS">
      Loop Detection for the Remote Authentication Dial-In User Service (RADIUS)
    </title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Donnelly" fullname="Mark Donnelly">
      <organization>Painless Security</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4 High St., Suite 134</street>
          <city>North Andover</city> <region>MA</region>
          <code>01845</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 (857)928-5967</phone>
        <email>mark@painless-security.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.painless-security.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="20" month="October" year="2022"/>

    <area>SEC</area>

    <workgroup>radextra BOF</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>
	This document describes attributes to be used in the Remote Authentication Dial-In User Service protocol <xref target="RFC2865"/> request proxying to enable the detection of loops.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
	This document describes attributes to be used in the Remote
	Authentication Dial-In User Service protocol
	<xref target="RFC2865"/> request proxying to enable the
	detection of loops.
      </t>
      <t>
	One common deployment for RADIUS servers is in an
	authentication network, to allow users from one organization
	to authenticate to systems in a different organization using
	their home organization credentials.  In complex
	authentication networks, authentication requests are proxied
	by multiple RADIUS proxy servers on their way from the
	supplicant to the authoritative identity providing RADIUS
	server.  A misconfiguration in the RADIUS servers can result
	in authentication requests being routed in a loop.  Loops not
	only cause the authentication in question to fail, but they
	can also cause a more general failure in the authentication
	network as the proxy RADIUS servers involved in the loop
	become busy and unresponsive to other traffic.
      </t>
      <t>
	The generally accepted method to prevent loops is for the
	proxy to add a Vendor-Specific Attribute to the RADIUS request
	and reject the authentication if that attribute is present.
	This is sufficient to prevent loops, but has drawbacks.
	First, this method relies upon operator configuration, which
	means that the loop detection will likely not be configured
	until after the operator has encountered and diagnosed loops
	at least once.  Second, this method requires the operator to
	acquire a Private Enterprise Number from IANA which, while
	free and easy to acquire, takes time and effort to acquire
	and is a barrier to implementation.  Finally, proxies may be
	configured to strip Vendor-Specific Attributes from requests,
	defeating the loop detection.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements Notation">
      <t>
	The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
	NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
	"OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
	in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Overview">
      <t>
	
      </t>
    </section>
      
    <section title="Proxy-Identifier Attribute">
      <t>
	This attribute MAY be used to record which RADIUS proxies have
	handled a given RADIUS request.  It MAY be used with any
	RADIUS request type, including authentication requests
	(Access-Request, Access-Accept, Access-Reject,
	Access-Challenge), and accounting requests
	(Accounting-Request, Accounting-Response).
      </t>

      <t>
	This attribute holds a value composed of a series of
	Type-Length-Value (TLV) sub-attributes.  Each sub-attribute
	contains an identifier for a RADIUS proxy.  The
	Proxy-Identifier MUST have at least one sub-attribute and MAY
	have more than one sub-attribute.  If multiple sub-attributes
	are present, a RADIUS proxy MUST match all of the
	sub-attributes in order to match the identifier.
      </t>

      <t>
	A summary of the Proxy-Identifier Sub-Attribute format is
	shown below. The fields are transmitted from left to right.
      </t>

      <artwork type="ascii-art">
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Proxy-        |  Length       | Value ...
|  Identifier-  |               |
|  Type         |               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      </artwork>

      <dl>
	<dt>
	  Proxy-Identifier-Type
	</dt>
	<dd>
	  Integer indicating which type of proxy identifier is being
	  communicated.
	</dd>
	
	<dt>
	  Length
	</dt>
	<dd>
	  Integer indicating the length of the value
	</dd>
	
	<dt>
	  Value
	</dt>
	<dd>
	  The value of the proxy identifier
	</dd>
	
      </dl>

      <section title="Proxy-Name">
	<dl>
	  <dt>
	    Proxy-Identifier-Type
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    1
	  </dd>
	  
	  <dt>
	    Length
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    2 + length(value)
	  </dd>
	  
	  <dt>
	    Value
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    The Proxy-Name.  This analogue of the Operator-Name <xref
	    target="RFC5580"/> indicates the organizational name for
	    the proxy.  For instance, a single logical proxy might
	    be run by multiple real servers, all of which share a
	    single Proy-Name value to indicate that they are logically
	    the same unit.
	  </dd>
	</dl>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Proxy-Identifier">
	<dl>
	  <dt>
	    Proxy-Identifier-Type
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    2
	  </dd>
	  
	  <dt>
	    Length
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    2 + length(value)
	  </dd>
	  
	  <dt>
	    Value
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    The Proxy-Identifier.  This analogue of the NAS-Identifier
	    <xref target="RFC2865"/> indicates the name of this
	    particular proxy server.  For instance, this could be used
	    to differntiate between multiple real servers running
	    within a single logical RADIUS proxy.
	  </dd>
	</dl>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Proxy-IPv4-Address">
	<dl>
	  <dt>
	    Proxy-Identifier-Type
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    3
	  </dd>
	  
	  <dt>
	    Length
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    6
	  </dd>
	  
	  <dt>
	    Value
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    The IPv4 address of this RADIUS proxy.  This SHOULD be the
	    address that was used as a destination for this RADIUS
	    request.  So, if a RADIUS proxy server has a routable IP
	    address mapped to a private IP address, the routable IP
	    address SHOULD be used.
	  </dd>
	</dl>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Proxy-IPv6-Address">
	<dl>
	  <dt>
	    Proxy-Identifier-Type
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    4
	  </dd>
	  
	  <dt>
	    Length
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    18
	  </dd>
	  
	  <dt>
	    Value
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    The IPv6 address of this RADIUS proxy.  This SHOULD be the
	    address that was used as a destination for this RADIUS
	    request.  So, if a RADIUS proxy server has a routable IP
	    address mapped to a private IP address, the routable IP
	    address SHOULD be used.
	  </dd>
	</dl>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Proxy-Port">
	<dl>
	  <dt>
	    Proxy-Identifier-Type
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    5
	  </dd>
	  
	  <dt>
	    Length
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    6
	  </dd>
	  
	  <dt>
	    Value
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    The UDP or TCP port of this RADIUS proxy.  This SHOULD be
	    the port that was used as a destination for this RADIUS
	    request.  So, if a RADIUS proxy server has a routable IP
	    address mapped to a private IP address, the routable IP
	    address port SHOULD be used.
	  </dd>
	</dl>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Configuration-Identifier">
	<dl>
	  <dt>
	    Proxy-Identifier-Type
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    6
	  </dd>
	  
	  <dt>
	    Length
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    2 + length(value)
	  </dd>
	  
	  <dt>
	    Value
	  </dt>
	  <dd>
	    The identifier for the server configuration used in this
	    routing.  If a server can be configured to handle requests
	    differently depending on the RADIUS client or request
	    data, then this SHOULD be used to indicate which
	    configuration the request used.
	  </dd>
	</dl>
      </section>
      
    </section>

    <section title="Server responsibilities">
      <t>
	The proxy SHOULD add a Proxy-Identifier attribute to any
	RADIUS request it receives, populated with information used to
	identify itself, before proxying a request to its next hop.
      </t>

      <t>
	When adding the Proxy-Identifier Attribute, the proxy MUST add
	at least one sub-attribute that accurately describes the
	proxy. The proxy MAY add more than one Proxy-Identifier
	sub-attribute that accurately describes the proxy.
      </t>

      <t>
	The proxy MUST inspect every RADIUS request it receives for
	the Proxy-Identifier attributes.  If an authentication request
	contains a Proxy-Identifier attribute that matches the current
	server, the proxy server MUST respond to the request with
	Access-Reject.  If an accounting request contains a
	Proxy-Identifier attribute that matches the current server,
	the proxy server MUST silently discard the request.
      </t>

      <t>
	The proxy MUST consider a Proxy-Identifier to be a match if
	all of the sub-attributes in the Proxy-Identifier Attribute
	match the proxy.  The proxy MUST NOT consider a
	Proxy-Identifier to be a match if any of the sub-attributes do
	not match the proxy.
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
	This document defines the Proxy-Identifier RADIUS Attribute
	(TBD), which should be assigned by IANA from the Unassigned
	block of RADIUS Attribute Types.
      </t>

      <t>
	This document adds a new namespace that requires registration:
	the Proxy-Identifier-Type.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
	This document was written using xml2rfc, as described in
	<xref target="RFC7749"/>
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;
      &rfc2865;
    </references>
    
    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc5580;
      &rfc7749;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
